Hello.
My name is Antoine Miné.
I will present you one application of the
OCaml programming language:
the Astrée static analyzer.
Astrée is a research project
that started in 2001
by a team at École normale supérieure
under the supervision of Patrick Cousot.
It lead to the design of a software
that is used in several industries
such as avionics and automotive industries.
It is available commercially.
It is also an example of a large program made in OCaml
Astrée is a static analyzer for C.
It checks for the absence of run-time errors
such as array overflows or memory errors
The check is static, at compile time
as opposed to testing.
It focuses on embedded critical C
a field where it is important to ensure
the absence of error
before the program is ever run
Astrée works directly on the original source code
without any help or annotation from the user.
To scale up to million-line size programs
Astrée must do approximations.
For instance, the values of a variable may
be modelled as an interval
which is an over-approximation
easily representable in memory
as a pair of bounds.
These approximations are always sound.
They would result in over-approximating
the set of behaviors of the program.
So that, if Astrée does not find any error
then there is actually no error
in the original source code.
Astrée is based on
the Abstract Interpretation framework
which helps in defining approximations
in such a sound way.
Due to over-approximation
the analysis may report false alarms.
Actually, Astrée employs dozens
of  such abstract domains
in addition to intervals
in order to be sufficiently precise.
Before its industrialization,
Astrée was used in academia
in order to check avionics code
from Airbus planes.
On this code, Astrée achieved
an unprecedented result
the proof of absence of run-time error,
that is, zero false alarm.
Now, Astrée is industrialized and
available commercially from the AbsInt company.
Now, why is OCaml such a great tool
to design a static analyzer?
There are two language features
that are used pervasively in Astrée.
The first one is Abstract data-types.
The union type in OCaml is a perfect tool
to manipulate abstract syntax trees.
Astrée manipulates a lot of abstract syntax trees
that represent parts of the program to analyze.
For instance, Astrée may need to evaluate
a C expression in the world of intervals.
Astrée will use pervasively pattern-matching
in order to iterate over the syntax tree.
and recognize special instructions to handle.
The second one is modules and functors.
Astrée is a very modular tool
that contains dozens of abstractions
that can be plugged in and out.
Each abstract domain is a module
with a type that represents
abstract sets of values
as well as operators to model in the abstract world
the effect of every instruction.
The Abstract Interpretation theory also features
a lot of higher order constructs
that allow designing new abstract domains
by combining and lifting existing ones.
These are naturally mapped to OCaml functors.
Astrée employes many such functors
in order to develop each language feature
and each abstraction
as independently as possible from the other ones.
We have functors to add disjunctions,
to add pointers, to add control structures,
and so on so forth.
This design has also allowed Astrée to evolve
quite significantly since 2001
while still reusing the abstractions
that were designed early on.
I should add that the static type checking
and type inference of OCaml
has helped us tremendously in designing Astrée
quickly and robustly.
Finally, Ocaml's native code compiler
has brought us all the efficiency we need
for a tool that can be used in industry.
To go further, you can check Astrée's webpage
at www.astree.ens.fr,
and check the publications.
There are also a couple of related projects.
This first one is the open-source Frama-C
verification platform
which includes a static analyzer,
also programmed in OCaml.
The other one is the Verasco project,
It aims at creating a static analyzer certified in Coq
following the success of the Compcert compiler.
As you see, the OCaml programming language
has been used
to design applications that are successful
in the real world.
I hope that you enjoyed this MOOC
and that you will build your own
successful OCaml application.